Hello and welcome to another walkthrough for
computer architecture for everybody. In the
previous walkthrough, we went through a simple
WAT WASM situation where we're talking
to JavaScript. This is not really CC code. It's
hello world, but it's not CC code. This is WASM
plus Java being run in a JavaScript context. And
the hello world is coming out of the console log
function in JavaScript. I want to shift gears a
little bit focusing still again on Hello World and
show you something for another one of my classes
C programming for everybody under the write C
option. So in this course I have a C autograder.
right now I'm just using the playground and
you can write C programs and then compile
them. So let's go ahead and write our C program.
Now I'm going to hit the run code here and you'll
see a little spinner going on and there's a bunch
of work and if you do the view source and you
watch the network I'm not going to show you the
whole network. What you'll see is this CC code is
being sent up to the CC server using a piece of
software called McrypTum which compiles CC code
and other things into WASM. Then this environment
will download the WASM and I've got it watching for
a string WASOM in the network requests and it will
download that WASM and then it will execute the WASM
and it will put the output here. I mean I already
executed it but I made a change hello world
exclamation. So in the next click it is going
to compile it compile to WASM inside the server
download the WASM back into the browser and then
execute the WASM in JavaScript. So it's it's going
to be boring. It's just going to work. But
watch for the spinner in the middle here. There
goes the See the spinner was there for just like
a quarter of a second. I ought to slow it down.
But it did that. And there is this aout WASM. And
if we take a look at the response, yeah, it's not
going to show it to us because it's binary
stuff. Okay. So, that was the a WASM that came
back. Now, that WASM executed with a JavaScript
framework to start that WASM up and then it
printed hello world. Now, standard io.h is in C.
Print F is in the C standard library. So what has
inscriptim done? Well, what incriptim has done is
it has compiled all of the standard libraries into
WASM. It has compiled our code into LA WASM. It's
linked it all together and sent down a really big
WASM because this pound include if you don't see
it just pulls a file in. And so that got compiled
into WASM 2. So, let's take a look at how much WASM
really came down. So, let's take a look here. This
is a dump of the WASM for Hello World. And there's
a lot here, but it's not that much, right? It's we
got let's see 3 C00 hex. I don't know how big that
is, but I just scrolled through the whole thing.
But this is not just my Hello World code. This is
hello world plus some of the standard library
and some of the standard io.h all compiled
into WASM. Now, now this now is self-contained
as WASM code ready to run inside of the browser.
And that's of course what happened when it ran
in the browser and out came hello world. But
there's a lot to it because we're pulling in the
C libraries and converting them to WASM as well.
So this is an ugly version of it. We can
take a look at a little prettier version of it by
looking at not much prettier. We can look at the
WAT. And so we're looking at the WAT here. This
was written to be readable. This this is the WAT
code editor for the Hello World. That's a pure WM
JavaScript example. And you can read it
and you'll change it in your autograder in a bit.
This is more like what WASM does because it ran the
inscription compiler and produced the WASM and then
I converted the WASM to WAT so that we could see
it. And we're not going to change this. There's
all kinds of stuff. FD write FD close f. That's
part of the standard library. And you see it's
really like busy stuff. It's calling things and
par setting parameters and pushing them on the
stack and calling them and making functions and
do we have any loops here? Let's see if we can
get to a loop. There's a block, right? There's
some there's some blocks. There's some loops,
right? And jumps and all kinds of stuff. This is
this is the output of a compiler that is writing
to a pseudo machine language in WAT. So, I'll
just scroll through this. That is a lot a wat
okay and is not very easy to see but it's pretty
yummy and delicious to the runtime environment
in JavaScript who has built an interpreter
much like the interpreter we built for the
CDC 6504 and it runs that as the interpreter.
Okay. So the key thing is is that I'm not going
to spend a lot of time having you learn
to code WAT. It's not intended for you to code
it. It's intended for compilers to produce it.
So just imagine that this C program that we're
writing is really like a high performance maybe
a video game shading library or something that
would then get compiled into WASM which would be
super high performant and then that WASM might
be recompiled into raw machine language by my
browser and then it'd be like super fast in the
browser and that's the whole that's literally
the whole point of WASM. The WASM is to make it
so you can write approaching machine code speed
code in a portable, safe, sandboxed way running
in the browser under the rules of JavaScript. And
inside that browser, you can mix code from many
sources and many trust domains and they can't
harm each other because they're all running in
individualized sandboxes. Okay, so I hope that
was a bit interesting about how we connect C
programming and an WM and how I use it in my
C programming for everybody course. Cheers.